Chapter 97.
The lamp.
Had you descended from the Peekquad's triworks to the Peekquad's folk where
the offduty watch were sleeping, for one single moment, you would have almost
thought you were standing in some illuminated shrine of canonized kings
and counselors. There they lay in their triangular oaken vaults, each mariner a
chiseled mutiness, a score of lamps flashing upon his hooded eyes. In
merchant men, oil for the sailor is more scarce than the milk of queens, to dress
in the dark, to eat in the dark and stumble in darkness to his pallet. This
is his usual lot. But the whaleman, as he seeks the food of light, so he lives
in light. He makes his birth an Aladdin's lamp and lays him down to it,
so that in the pitchest night the ship's black hull still houses an illumination.
See with what entire freedom the whaleman takes his handful of lamps,
often but old bottles and vials, though to the copper cooler at the triworks,
and replenishes them there as mugs of ale at a vat. He burns to the purest of
oils in its unmanufactured and therefore unvvisiated state a fluid unknown to
solar lunar or astral contrivances ashore. It is as sweet as early grass
butter in April. He goes and hunts for his oil so as to be sure of its
freshness and genuiness, even as the traveler on the prairie hunts up his own supper of game.